<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Jewes message to their brethern in Holland; and a new letter touching their further proceedings sent from the kingdom of Scotland: with the arrive [sic] of some of them near Aberdeen, in a small ship, whose sails were white cranched sattin, their ropes and tackling silk of the sames colour; and their food on board only rice and pure honey. Also, another letter from Dr. Serarias, to doctor Homes; the rendovouzing of sexteen hundred thousand in the Turks dominions; and threescore thousand come into Europe; the Great Turks sad and fearful dream; and strange miracles performed by the Captain-general of the wandring Israelites; a description of their persons, habits, and weapons; the granting of liberty of conscience to all excepting infidels; a prophecie touching the downfal of Babylon in 66, and the year of reformation for the Gospel to be preached throughout all nations.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46883</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J743</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220740</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832132</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832132</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36603</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46883)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36603)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1779:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Jewes message to their brethern in Holland; and a new letter touching their further proceedings sent from the kingdom of Scotland: with the arrive [sic] of some of them near Aberdeen, in a small ship, whose sails were white cranched sattin, their ropes and tackling silk of the sames colour; and their food on board only rice and pure honey. Also, another letter from Dr. Serarias, to doctor Homes; the rendovouzing of sexteen hundred thousand in the Turks dominions; and threescore thousand come into Europe; the Great Turks sad and fearful dream; and strange miracles performed by the Captain-general of the wandring Israelites; a description of their persons, habits, and weapons; the granting of liberty of conscience to all excepting infidels; a prophecie touching the downfal of Babylon in 66, and the year of reformation for the Gospel to be preached throughout all nations.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for George Freeman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno dom. 1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jews --  Turkey --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Turkey --  Ethnic relations --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36603:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Jewes Meſſage TO Their Brethren in HOLLAND; AND A New Letter touching their further Proceedings ſent from the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland:</hi> With the arrive of ſome of them near <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> in a ſmall Ship, whoſe Sails were white branched Sattin, their Ropes and Tackling Silk of the ſame Colour; and their Food on Board only Rice and pure Honey.</p>
            <p>Alſo, another Letter from Dr. Serarias, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Doctor <hi>Homes;</hi> The Rendevouzing of Sixteen Hundred Thouſand in the <hi>Turks</hi> Dominions; and Threeſcore Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand come into <hi>Europe;</hi> The <hi>Great Turks</hi> ſad and fearful <hi>Dream;</hi> and ſtrange Miracles performed by the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain-General of the <hi>Wandring Iſraelites;</hi> A Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Perſons, Habits, and Weapons; the granting of <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> to all except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Infidels;</hi> A Prophecie touching the Downfal of <hi>Babylon</hi> in 66, and the Year of Reformation for the Goſpel to be preached throughout all NATIONS.</p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>George Freem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> Anno Dom. 1665.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:36603:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36603:2"/>
            <head>A New Letter ſent from <hi>Scotland,</hi> concerning the further Proceedings of the <hi>JEWS.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving received a more full account of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the <hi>Jews,</hi> I ſhall here preſent you with ſuch <hi>Occurrences,</hi> in this juncture of time, wherein ſcarce any thing elſe, is either talkt of, or lookt after, in compariſon of them. The whole World we ſee is out of order, nothing to be expected but Inteſtine Broils, and whether the Lord will be pleaſed in the midſt of theſe Combuſtions to call in his Antient People, and magnifie his Name in them, He onely knoweth. On the 23 of <hi>October,</hi> by the foulneſſe of the weather and ſtorms, put into <hi>Aberdeen</hi> a Ship, from whence ſhe came, 'tis uncertain; but the Profeſſour of that City, of the Tongues and Languages, having Notice thereof, went down unto them, and by their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe perceived they ſpoke broken <hi>Hebrew,</hi> and bound for <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam,</hi> as was intimated by a Letter in <hi>High-Dutch,</hi> to have Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with their Brethren (the <hi>Jews</hi>) there: Which Letter further relates, That there is Sixteen hundred thouſand of them together in <hi>Arabia,</hi> and that there came into <hi>Europe</hi> Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Thouſand more; withall, that they have had many Encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with the <hi>Turks,</hi> defeating ſeveral Bodies, and killing many Thouſands, none being able to ſtand againſt them. They give Liberty of <hi>Conſcience</hi> to all, except the <hi>Turks,</hi> endeavouring the utter Ruine and Extirpation of them. But for the ſhip, the Sails thereof are white branched Sattin, and all their Ropes are Silk of the ſame Colour; and in the Sails was this Inſcription in fair Red Characters,</p>
            <q>Theſe are of the Ten Tribes of Iſrael.</q>
            <p>Which was to diſcover them to be <hi>Jews:</hi> Their Food on board was onely Rice and Honey: Their Habit [or Cloathing] Black
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:36603:3"/> Black and Blew. It ſeemſ they have ſent to moſt of the chief Cities in the World to their Brethren, to give them Notice of their Proceedings, to the end they may come and joyn with them. The <hi>Great Turk</hi> having had a <hi>Dream,</hi> that a <hi>Jew</hi> had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Crown from his Head, reſolved to put all to death within his Dominions; but his Council diſſwaded him from that <hi>Bloody Deſign.</hi> The <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Hoſt are ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to increaſe daily, and that many of them believe in the true Meſſias, and that it was the Saviour of the <hi>World</hi> that was crucified at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>This was ſent in a Letter t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Oxford, <hi>Dated from</hi> Scotland, <date>
                     <hi>Novemb.</hi> 15.</date>
               </dateline> 
               <hi>The following Letters were ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt from Dr.</hi> Ser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rias, <hi>to Dr.</hi> Homes, <hi>Mr.</hi> Bruce, <hi>and others.</hi>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce my laſt of the Proceedings of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> We have had Expreſſes not onely from <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> but <hi>Tunnis</hi> alſo; That this Year no Carrivan is to go to <hi>Mecha,</hi> by reaſon the City is beſieged by the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who appear in great Numbers, and are ſaid to be ſent by the Ten Tribes to be the Fore-runners:</p>
            <p>From <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> we have received very good News, and likewiſe many of our Chriſtian Merchants have received the like from <hi>Alexandria,</hi> The Particulars of which is, that the Baſhaw of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> with the King of <hi>Arabia,</hi> made uſe of a Carravan, that is, an Army of Sixty Thouſand Men, and marched toward <hi>Mecha,</hi> and being within one days Iourney of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſent out a Troop to take notice how things were, which Troop having ſeen this People lying in Tents about the Citie, and hearing that they profeſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> reported this to the Baſhaw who for all that reſolved to march on with his Forces and coming within ſight of the City, diſcovered an innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Multitude of People coming out of their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36603:3"/> Tents. Whereupon the Turks advanced up againſt them, gave fire, &amp; diſcharged ſeveral Volleys of round ſhot; but after a little fighting a pannick fear took them and terror ſeized on them, making them cry out <hi>Who is able to fight with theſe People, ſeeing our Arrows and Shot return back upon our ſelves.</hi> So the Turks lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving off fighting, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eturned Home, and the Iſraelites into their Tents without purſuing them. This Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front cauſed the Baſhaw and King of the Moors, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row-out all Egypt and Arabia, to impoſe on the Iews in all their Dominions a new Tax five times greater then it was before. And the Baſhaw, the better to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himſelf what this People were ſent ten Iews to them who found them to be Iſraelites, and that they ſpake <hi>Hebrew,</hi> ſaying, they were ſent before to remain at <hi>Meka</hi> till the reſt of their Brethren came, for that the time was now come, that they ſhould return unto their own Land of their Fore-Fathers, which others had uſurped and taken from them. Another Letter ſaith, that the Commander of <hi>Meka</hi> ſent <hi>4</hi> Troops to oppoſe them, but not one returned and that divers Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravans and great Bodies have bin wholly defeated by the ſaid <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> and that twelve thouſand Turks coming from a City called <hi>Metai,</hi> near <hi>Meka</hi> were alſo routed, and eight thouſand ſlain upon the Place, their own Swords and Muskets turning againſt themſelves. Of the ten Iews that were ſent, ſix re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained with their Brethren, and but <hi>4</hi> returned to the Turks. As for the great Prophet in <hi>North-Skilton,</hi> Doctor <hi>Colloneſt</hi> hath bin at his Houſe in a Town called <hi>Long-Ditch,</hi> where he heard theſe things out of his own Mouth. That in the Year <hi>1661.</hi> he medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on the Scriptures ſpeaking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter Times;</hi>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:36603:4"/> of the great Multitude: yet withall heard of other <hi>Jews</hi> that ſeveral of them ſpake the <hi>Holy Tongue;</hi> and that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever goeth to contend with this People in Battel, are preſently vanquiſhed, and ſlein.</p>
            <p>They have already poſſeſt themſelves of ſeveral Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Cities, putting all the Inhabitants to the Sword, the <hi>Jews</hi> onely excepted. They are a People of a middle ſtature, their Bodies comely, their Complexions fair: This Party ſaw no Woman amongſt them, nor any other Arms, beſides thoſe above-mentioned; their Horſes are many, their Attire blew, and their <hi>Tents</hi> black. From the aforeſaid City of <hi>Sus,</hi> the whole Hoſt of them might be plainly and diſtinctly viewed the whole Week, and might ſee their Fires and Smoak aſcending; but on the Sabbath, neither of both could be diſcerned throughout the whole Camp, or Hoſt.</p>
            <p>Several of them being commanded up to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for a <hi>Braſs-Tamber,</hi> or <hi>Trumpet;</hi> and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the finding it, three times to ſound it, and then all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be gathered into one Univerſal Church: their Leader is of an extraordinary diſcerning Spirit for no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner doth he ſee a Man, but he knows his Mind, and the thoughts of his Heart, treating them with very much hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and reſpect. And coming to a <hi>River</hi> not Foorda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble he conſulted with his Officers and unanimouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to implore the great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od by Petition and Prayer, to deliver them as he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne their Fore-Fathers, and to ſhew them ſome Mira<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> to evence them of the truth of the great Meſsias born of a Virgin, to be the Saviour of the World: whereupon, ſo great and wonderful a Work was wrought, that the great Waters immediatly divided, as ſoon as they had ended Prayers, and the whole Army in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>cked over even as it were upon dry Land.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
